<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation for encouragement of cloth-manufactories</title>
            <author>Scotland. Council of Trade.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614913</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2761:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation for encouragement of cloth-manufactories</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Council of Trade.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head: royal seal with initials "J R".</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clothing trade --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:176079:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>J R</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <hi>A PROCLAMATION</hi> For Encouragement of Cloth-Manufactories.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>AMES</hi> by the Grace of GOD, King of Great <hi>Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith,</signed>
               <salute>To  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>  Macers of Our Privy Council, or Meſſengers at Arms, Cur Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially conſtitute, Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Forasmuch, as by ſeveral Laws, and Acts of Parliament, and particularly by the 12th. Act of the 3d Parliament of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, of ever bleſſed memory; All Merchants, and other Perſons whatſomever, are ſtrictly prohibit, and diſcharged to Import into this Kingdom, any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Cloths, or Stuffs made of Wool, with Certification, that all ſuch Goods, as ſhall be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported contrary thereto, ſhall be burnt and deſtroyed, and the Importers, and Reſetters thereof Fined in the Value of the ſaids Goods: As alſo, by an Act of Our Privy Council, of the date, the 14. day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1685. The Lords thereof, for the Encouragement of Manufactories, did give full Power and Warrand to the undertakers therein, or thoſe to be Intruſted by them, to ſeize on all Forraign Cloth, and Searges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Imported within this Kingdom, contrary to Law; and did thereby ſtrictly Prohibit, and Diſcharge all Perſons whatſomever, either by Colluſion, or otherways, to Import, or Traffique within this Kingdom, concerning the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying, Vending, or Selling any Forraign Woollen Cloth, and others aforſaid, within the ſame, under the Pains and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties made thereagainſt: And likewiſe, did thereby Diſcharge the wearing of all Woollen Cloth, and Searges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that which is Native, under the pain of 500. Merks <hi>Scots</hi> Money, for each Tranſgreſſion. The Perſons challenged being always obliged to declare upon Oath, from whom they had any of the ſaids Prohibit Goods: And likewiſe, We, by Our Royal Proclamation, of the date, the 16. day of <hi>September.</hi> 1686. By advice of Our Privy Council, did Revive and Renew all Laws made in Favours of Manufactories. Prohibiting, and Diſcharging the Importing, or Wearing what is thereby Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited. And did Require and Command the ſamen to be put in due and vigorous Execution, every manner of way, as is thereby preſcribed, and did thereby Prohibit and Diſcharge the Importing or Wearing of all <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Cloth; as alſo the wearing of all Stuffs, or prohibited Cloths, abroad, or in the Streets, under the pretence of Night-Gowns, or Night-Dreſſes, under the Pains contained in Our Proclamation, and Acts of Parliament. Notwithſtanding of which Acts, tending ſo much to the advancement of Manufactories, within this Kingdom, and thereby to the general advantage of the Nation. The Merchants, and others have Imported great Quantities of Prohibit Forraign Cloths, and Stuffs, to the great diſcouragement of the ſaid Manufactories; the conſiderable loſs and prejudice of the Kingdom, and manifeſt breach, and contempt of the Laws, which We underſtand to proceed from the not putting of the ſaids Laws to due Execution againſt the Contraveeners: Therefore, We, with advice of Our Council of Trade, do hereby Revive and renew all the ſaids Laws, and other Acts of Parliament, and Council, for the Encouragement of Manufactories, in all the Heads and Articles thereof; And Ordain, that all who have Imported any ſuch Forraign Cloths, or Stuffs, be proceeded againſt, before Our Council of Trade, conform to the tenor of the ſaids Acts. And further, for the Encouragement of the Cloth-Manufactorie already ſet up, and all thoſe that in time coming, ſhall be ſet up within this Kingdom, We, with advice foreſaid, do ſtrictly Prohibit and Diſcharge all manner of Perſons whatſomever, to buy any Forraign Cloth, Searges, Cairſeys, Freizes and mill'd D<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogats, all made o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wool, in time coming, or to make any Wearing Cloths thereof, in caſe they have any of the ſaids Cloths or Stuffs by them already, under the pain of 500. merks <hi>Scots.</hi> And to the effect, that no man may pretend Ignorance, whether Cloth be Forraign, or Native, We for diſtinguiſhing of the ſamen, do Ordain all Manufactories of Cloth, to have a Seal, which ſhall be put upon every Piece of Cloth, made therein, under the pain of confiscation of the ſamen; And that all other Perſons, making Cloth above the Price of three Pounds <hi>Scots,</hi> ſhall have the Seal of the adjacent Town, appended thereto, under the Penalty above-written, and the Magiſtrats of each Burgh, are hereby Ordained to append the ſamen, upon their making Faith, that the ſaid Cloth was made within the Kingdom. For appending of which Seal, the Preſenters o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Cl<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> are to pay two ſhilling <hi>Scots</hi> for ilk Piece. And in regard the Tailors have generally been the greateſt Traffiquers, in Buying, and Selling the foreſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit Goods; Therefore, We do hereby prohibit all Tailors, to Buy, or make any of the foreſaids prohibite Goods, under the Pain of 20. <hi>lib. Scots</hi> for ilk Tranſgreſſion, <hi>toties quoties.</hi> And that Our Pleaſure herein may be known, OUR WILL IS, and We Charge you ſtrictly, and Command, that incontinent theſe Our Letters ſeen ye paſs to the Mercat-Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and all other Places needfull, and there in Our Royal Name, and Authority, by open Proclamation, make publication of Our Pleaſure in the Premiſſes, that punctual obedience may be given thereto, and none pretend Ignorance.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                  <date>the Fifteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred eighty Years. And of Our Reign the Fourth Year.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per Actum Dominorum Concilii Commercii. Ro: Maine Cls. Concilii Commercii.</signed>
               <lb/>
GOD ſave the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred <hi>Majeſty: Anno DOM.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
